בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is כ"ב *Kaf Beis*, זבחים
*Zevachim* 22. We pick up at five lines from the bottom of
כ"ב עמוד ב׳ *Kaf Beis amud beis*. We're in the middle of
an extended discussion about רחיצת ידים ורגלים *rechitzas yadayim v'raglayim* and the
last piece of this difficult סוגיא *sugya* around that yesterday about when
they become invalid,
the water that's drawn, and the last piece here discusses the actual
כיור kiyor *kiyor*, the actual basin that was used to wash from.
So let's take a look. גופא *Gufa*, it was taught or we
taught earlier. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose barbi Chanina. *Amar
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina*, this is again four lines from the bottom
of כ"א עמוד ב׳ *Kaf Aleph amud beis*. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא כל כיור kiyor. שאין בו כדי לקדש ארבעה כהנים kohanim ממנו
mimmennu? אין מקדשין בו *Amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, kol kiyor she'ein
bo kidei lekadesh arba kohanim mimenu ein mikadshin bo*. Any basin that
does not have sufficient for being used for that four כהנים kohanim?
*kohanim* could wash their hands from it, you cannot use it for
the קידוש ידים ורגלים kidush yadayim veraglayim *kiddush yadayim v'raglayim*. שנאמר
*Shene'emar*, as the פסוק *pasuk* says, ורחצו ממנו verachatzu mimmennu משה ואהרן
ובניו *v'rachatzu mimenu Moshe v'Aharon u'vanav*. And Moshe, Aharon, and his children
were washed from it and it's being read to mean at the
same time they could do it, although they weren't exactly all serving
at the same time even though Moshe served as a כהן Kohen
*kohen* he did not do it at the same time Aharon and
his sons served as כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*. But nevertheless, it's read to
mean that it has to be possible for four כהנים kohanim *kohanim*
to do it. It's interesting the phrase כל כיור kiyor *kol kiyor*,
any כיור kiyor? *kiyor*. How many כיורים *kiyorim* did they have? You
know, are they just talking about the כיור kiyor. *kiyor* that was
in the actual בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* and describing historically
that that was the requirement of the כיור kiyor *kiyor* or if
you ever had to make a new one, that's what it certainly
what it sounds like, but we'll see also the question will be
as we've already seen is you can use a כלי שרת kli
shares *kli shares* as well, put water in a כלי שרת kli
shares *kli shares* and wash from a כלי שרת kli shares *kli
shares*. So we'll see if this applies to that as well. מיתבי
*Masvei*, I'll ask you on this says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*: כל
הכלים מקדשין בין שיש בהם רביעית revi’it. בין שאין בהם רביעית Revi'is,
ובלבד שיהו כלי שרת kli shares *Kol hakelim mikadshin, bein sheyeish bahem
revi'is bein she'ein bahem revi'is, u'vilvad sheyehu kli shares*. You can use
all types of vessels to do קידוש ידים ורגלים kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim.
*kiddush yadayim v'raglayim*,
whether they have a רביעית Revi'is *revi'is* or not a רביעית Revi'is,
*revi'is*, provided that it's a כלי שרת kli shares *kli shares*. So
we already saw that it has to be a כלי שרת kli
shares? *kli shares*, it has to be on the grounds of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, okay, but here it says that
it does not matter how much it contains, it can even contain
less than a רביעית Revi'is, *revi'is* which is quite surprising because as
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* points out even for normal washing of hands that
we do, you know, now which is for
טומאה *tumah* purposes that required at least a רביעית Revi'is? *revi'is*. So
this is quite shocking. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
and certainly it seems that you do not need to do it
with a four people, enough water that four כהנים kohanim, *kohanim* could
wash their hands from it. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה *Amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava* said רב אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda bar Ahava*:
בקודח בתוכו *bikode'ach b'tocho*. You make, carve a hole in it. Now
what exactly does that mean? So what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it
means is you basically put this כלי שרת kli shares *kli shares*,
you have a big basin and you make a hole in the
basin and into that hole you insert this כלי שרת kli shares
*kli shares*. So the כיור kiyor *kiyor* contains four לוג *log* and
it comes from the כיור kiyor *kiyor* through the כלי kli? *kli*
onto the hands of the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*, okay, which would mean
that yes, if you were to just do a כלי Kli, *kli*
by itself it would need to be enough for four כהנים kohanim...
*kohanim*.
But here because it's coming from the כיור kiyor *kiyor*, you know
this even if it's a very tiny כלי *kli* it's essentially functioning
like a spout. Now that's a little bizarre because then it's not
really you're washing your hands from the כלי *kli*, you're washing your
hands from the basin and you've affixed a כלי *kli* to work
as a spout. But presumably that's the חידוש chidush *chiddush*. The חידוש
chidush? *chiddush* is that no, conceptually, right, it wouldn't work if it
was not sanctified, if it was not a כלי שרת kli shares
*kli shares*. So conceptually you are washing your hands from the כלי
*kli*, not from the basin, but because it's coming from a source
that is containing four לוג *log* and the way you currently have
it constructed even though it's coming from the כלי *kli*, four כהנים
Kohanim *kohanim* could wash their hands from this כלי *kli*, this tiny
כלי *kli* because of the construction that you have created. Therefore that
suffices. That seems to be the חידוש chidush, *chiddush* according to רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* understands this very differently. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
says that what this means, if you look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
קודח Kodeach מתוכו *kode'ach m'tocho*, third תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* on the page,
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says: פירוש שנוטל ממנו mimmennu. בכלי קטן וכשר לקדש
בו דכיון דבאין מכלי גדול בהאי גוונא לקמן *Peirush shenoteil mimenu b'kli
katan v'kasher lekadesh bo d'keivan d'ba'in mikli gadol b'hai gavna lakaman*. Okay,
so תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says קודח *kode'ach* doesn't literally mean you carve
a hole in the basin. It means that you removed water from
the basin. You took your smaller vessel and you dunked it in
the basin, your vessel, and then you washed your hands from the
vessel. So it's coming the source of it is similar to רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* but doesn't demand as much as רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. As
long as it is sourced from water that had enough for four
כהנים kohanim, *kohanim* then this water it's sort of like a status
of the water. The water is כשר kosher, *kasher* because it's coming
from a source that had enough, so it's not defining the כיור
kiyor *kiyor* as it were because now your כיור kiyor *kiyor* isn't
the כיור kiyor *kiyor* it's a כלי *kli* and this כלי *kli*
doesn't have enough for four. כהנים, kohanim, but it's defining of the
water. The water has to come from something that was held in
a כלי שרת—from kli shares something, a type of a כיור kiyor.
that had enough for four כהנים kohanim, to wash their hands. Okay,
so that's how we're explaining it. Now, והממנו אמר רחמנא, Vehamimmennu amar
Rachmana,
so doesn't it say ממנו? mimmennu So what's the question? So רש״י
Rashi says the question is how can you use a כלי שרת
kli shares at all? It says ממנו. mimmennu But of course תוספות
Tosafos says, well, you know, that's explicit like we know the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol would wash his hands from a כלי שרת kli
shares, on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's not just a challenge to
this statement of רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. So תוספות Tosafot says that
the question actually is different. The question here is
that even if a כלי שרת kli shares? is כשר, Kosher. it
has to be like the כיור. kiyor. So how is this good
if the כיור kiyor. itself needed to contain enough water for four
כהנים? Shouldn't the same requirement apply to the כלי? Doesn't it have
to function like the כיור? Kiyor, So that's how תוספות Tosafot understands
it. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר רחמנא
ורחצו. Amar Rachmana verachatzu.
So it says או בגישתם אל המזבח לשרת ורחצו, o begishtam el
hamizbeach leshares verachatzu, they should wash their hands. So it repeats the
word they should wash their hands. It didn't have to say that.
It said ורחצו ממנו ve-rachatzu mimmennu. לרבות כלי שרת lerabbos k’lei shares
to tell you that it doesn't have to just be from the
כיור. Kiyor. Other ways that they can wash their hands. So for
רש״י Rashi that's fundamentally the לימוד limud that you can use a
כלי שרת kli shares, and that was the question, how do you
know you can use a כלי שרת? kli shares And for תוספות
the חידוש is that a כלי שרת kli sharet, is also good
and it doesn't, you know, as long as it's coming from the
water and from a כיור Kiyor, that contained that amount, the כלי
שרת kli sharet itself does not have to be exactly like the
כיור kiyor. as long as the water is sourced in that כיור
kiyor. or the כלי שרת kli sharet. itself has enough for four
כהנים. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So now we know that you can use a כלי שרת kli
sharet, and the כיור kiyor. has to contain water for four כהנים
and the כלי שרת kli sharet has to somehow be either itself
contain enough of that water or be connected to that water in
some way. Okay, אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So now, so one moment.
The גמרא Gemara says like this. לרבות כלי שרת. lerabbos k’lei shares.
אי הכי כלי חול נמי? i hachi k’lei chol nami? How do
you know ורחצו? verachatzu? If it's broadening what can be used and
it can even be a כלי שרת, kli sharet? then why do
you limit it to a כלי שרת? kli sharet Maybe even a
non-sanctified vessel? אמר אביי כלי חול לא
מצית אמרת. Amar Abaye k’lei chol lo masis amart. No, no, you
can't say that you can use a non-sanctified vessel מקל וחומר
מכנו. mikkal vachomer mikkanno. You can learn it from the basin, the
base of the basin, okay, the stand that the basin was on.
It says ועשית כיור נחשת וכנו נחשת לרחצה. veasita kiyor nechoshet vekanno
nechoshet lerachtza.
So you, you know, make also it—the תורה Torah explicitly says that
there has to be a base and also out of copper. Okay,
and now what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? ומה כנו שנמשך עמו
אינו
מקדש—the uma kanno shenimshach immo eino mikadesh base of the basin which
was one piece with the basin and was sanctified and it was,
you know,
the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha was used to sanctify it and make
it a כלי שרת, Kli sharet so if anything should be able
to function like the basin, you would think it would be the
base, and nevertheless it cannot do that. Now, it’s not clear how
we know it can't. We're assuming it can't. Now you also might
be thinking functionally how does it? So תוספות says well, you know,
imagine that it was like a turned over pot and that the
basin, you know, or the sink or whatever, you know, was
like and the hollow of the pot was facing the ground and
then, you know, it was sort of like a half dome and
then the basin was built on top of that.
So sort of like as a pedestal. So in theory you could
remove the base and turn it, you know, reverse it and use
the hollow and use that to wash your hands. And you're not
allowed to do that. Okay, that we're taking for granted.
So if that you can't use, אינו מקדש כלי חול שאינו נמשך
עמו אינו דין שאינו מקדש, eino mikadesh k’lei chol she’eino nimshach immo
eino din she’eino mikadesh,
so certainly you should not be able to use something that is
a non-sanctified vessel. Of course with that קל וחומר kal vachomer you
shouldn't even be able to use a כלי שרת either. Okay, but
anyway that's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara, has to say about this.
וכנו מנלן? vekanno minalan? Okay, how do you know that you can't
use the pedestal, the base? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, יכול יהא כנו מקדש כדרך
שהכיור מקדש? yachol yehei kanno mikadesh k’derech shehakiyor mikadesh? Maybe you could
use the base of the basin, the base of the כיור kiyor.
to do קידוש ידים ורגלים kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim, the same way you
can use the כיור iyor itself? תלמוד לומר ועשית כיור נחשת וכנו
נחשת לרחצה. Talmud lomar veasita kiyor nechoshet vekanno nechoshet lerachtza.
You should make a כיור kiyor, of copper and the pedestal of
copper for washing. לנחשת הוקשה ולא לדבר אחר. lenechoshet huksha velo ledavar
acher. So it's funny because the next word after וכנו נחשת vekanno
nechoshet is לרחצה, lerachtza, so you might have said specifically you can
use the pedestal for washing. But the דרשה drasha is because it
repeats the word נחשת, nechoshet, it could have just said כיור וכנו
נחשת, kiyor vekanno nechoshet, you know, but because it repeats the word
נחשת, nechoshet, it's— It's coming to tell you that the only similarity
of these two is that they're made out of נחשת, nechoshet, but
they are not functionally similar in any way and you cannot use
the the pedestal for for doing קידוש Kiddush ידים ורגלים.
All right, so that's how we know and that's the קל וחומר.
kal va-chomer. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה
מר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי לרבינא. Amar lei Mar Zutra bereih de-Rav
Mari le-Ravina. But Mar Zutra then said to Ravina: מה לכנו שכן
אין עשוי לתוכו, mah le-khanno she-ken ein asui le-tokho, תאמר בכלי חול
שעשוי לתוכו? tomar bi-khli chol she-asui le-tokho? So besides the question that
you could have used that קל וחומר kal va-chomer also for a
כלי שרת, okay, it has another question. There's a reason why you
can't use the the pedestal, because the hollow of it is not
made for holding things, right? If it's the upturned, turned-up upside-down pot,
so that doesn't really... it's a vessel not made for containing water
or for the ability to hold liquids or to hold something, maybe
it's categorically different. But maybe a non-כלי שרת that is made as
a basin, that is made to hold, you know, as a receptacle,
maybe that's better than the כנו khanno and maybe that can be
used. So you cannot exclude, you know, כלי חול kli chol based
on a based on a קל וחומר kal va-chomer based on the
based on the pedestal. So תאמר בכלי חול שעשוי לתוכו? tomar bi-khli
chol she-asui le-tokho? אלא ממנו למעוטי כלי חול. ella mimmennu le-ma’utei kli
chol. Okay,
so we have two words: ורחצו ממנו. ve-rachatzu mimmennu
So by the way this makes it also really sound like רש"י
Rashi, that there's it's not a discussion going back to the idea
of the quantity of water, it's all a question of figuring out
whether you can use a כלי שרת. So we have two competing
words. Okay, one word is ירחצו, yirchatzu, okay, which is broad, it
repeats washing to say there's other things you can use, you can
even use a כלי שרת, but then it says ורחצו ממנו which
was the challenge of the גמרא, Gemara, from it, only from the
basin. So that tension, only from the basin but we're broadening, allows
us to sort of come down in a middle place. It can
be a כלי שרת that is like the basin and also is
made as a receptacle, but it can't be a כלי חול, kli
chol, it can't be something that's not sanctified. אלא ממנו למעוטי כלי
חול. ella mimmennu le-ma’utei kli chol. אי הכי כלי שרת נמי? ei
hachi kli sharet nami?
So if ממנו is saying only the basin, exclude כלי שרת? הא
רבי רחמנא ירחצו. ha ribbi rachmana yirchatzu. No, we have these two
competing words: ירחצו yirchatzu broadens beyond just the basin and ממנו limits.
ומה ראית? u-mah ra’ita?
And what's the difference? The obvious difference is: זה טעון משיחה וזה
אינו טעון משיחה כמותו, zeh ta’un meshichah ve-zeh eino ta’un meshichah kemoto,
וזה אינו טעון משיחה כמותו. ve-zeh eino ta’un meshichah kemoto. You know,
a כלי שרת is also anointed with the שמן המשחה. shemen ha-mishchah.
So okay, it's not a fixed piece of furniture, but you could
certainly view it as a mini-כיור. kiyor It's something that's made for
holding water, okay, and therefore it's similar enough that that's what we
include by the ירחצו. yirchatzu. All right, so that's how we know
כלי חול kli chol and presumably it has to contain the amount
for four כהנים, except in some case where their water was drawn
from the basin in some way.
All right, now אמר ריש לקיש. amar Reish Lakish. Now one last
sort of discussion relating to, again, not the act of washing of
קידוש ידים ורגלים, but the waters that are contained within the within
the כיור. kiyor, אמר ריש לקיש: amar Reish Lakish: כל המשלימין למי
מקוה משלימין למי כיור. kol ha-mashlimin le-mei mikveh mashlimin le-mei kiyor. לרביעית...
le-revi’it... לרביעית אינו משלים. le-revi’it eino mashlim. Okay,
anything that can can get you to the 40 סאה se'ah of
a מקוה, mikveh, a מקוה mikveh has to have 40 סאה se'ah
and about enough, you know, that one person's can totally immerse themselves
in. And
it doesn't have to be fully 40 סאה se'ah of water. There
could be some things that are somewhat similar to water that can
that can get you to the 40 סאה. se'ah. And you can't
be טובל tovel in them them-themselves and they can't make up the
majority of the 40 סאה, se'ah, but if you have 39 or
38 or even 21 סאה se'ah and you have these these other
types of liquids we'll call them, okay, then it's considered like the
מקוה mikveh has 40 סאה. se'ah. What are these things? Well we'll
take a look in the גמרא Gemara in a minute. It's listed
in a משנה Mishnah in מקוואות, Mikva'ot, but the the one that's
really gonna focus on is טיט הנרוק tit ha-nerok or הנידוק, ha-nidok,
which is a plaster that is like pourable or very thin plaster,
thin watery plaster. All right, so that can make up that can
get you some of the... it's like when you have a מנין,
minyan, right? There's debates: do you need all 10 men davening? Is
it enough that six men daven, seven men daven, three men are
also there? So that's the idea of being משלים. mashlim. Okay, so
he says anything that you could use to be משלים mashlim the
40 סאה se'ah of a מקוה, mikveh,
as long as you're totally immersing in the water part and now
it's just a question of getting the right quantity, so that type
of a liquid or whatever you can also use for the quantity
of you need enough for four כהנים of water in the כיור.
kiyor But you can't use it for רביעית. Revi'is If you need
a, you know, like your... like when you're washing your hands that
you would do to purify them, whether, you know, it's what they
would do in the time of the גמרא, Gemara. your hands were
were considered a שני לטומאה, sheni le-tumah, so כהנים... כהנים beforehand handling
תרומה Trumah had to wash their hands, what we do before eating
bread, for that when you require a רביעית, Revi'is okay then you
cannot add this type of liquid that's such a tiny שיעור Shiur
that it all has to be water. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this,
you know, תוספות has a different explanation what רביעית Revi'it. we're talking
about, but I'll get to that in a minute when we see
it in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this,
לימותי
מאי, Limutei mai, what type of liquid are you saying works for
מקוה Mikvah and the כיור, kiyor. but not for the רביעית, Revi'it.
okay, לימותי מאי, Limutei mai, what do you exclude? אילימא לימותי טיט
הנרוק Ileima limutei titani dok or some have the גרסא Girsa טיט
הנרוק, Titani rok, what I think is actually a better גרסא. Girsa.
If you're coming to exclude plaster that is pourable, a type of
a thin plaster. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דפרה
שוחה ושותה ממנו, I de-parash shocheh ve-shoteh mimeno, if a cow can
just bend down it said and drink from it, אפילו רביעית נמי,
Afilu revi'is nami, then that's enough considered water that you can use
it even for washing your hands for the that רביעית, Revi'it. you
know, and ואי אין פרה שוחה ושותה ממנו, Ve-ie ein parash shoteh
ve-shocheh mimeno, and if it's not drinkable by a cow or it's
not you know, whether it's
a cow would want to because of the taste is different but
it's not liquidy enough for a cow to drink it, this might
be what it means, אפילו למקוה נמי אינו משלים, Afilu le-mikvah nami
eino mashlim, and also it can't get you the right שיעור Shiur
for a מקוה. Mikvah. Now that's very, very strange. תוספות says, you
know, there's all of these different definitions in מקואות Mikvaos about how
what is the consistency of this טיט הנרוק, Titani rok, and none
of them use this definition of a cow being able to bend
down and drink from it. So it's bizarre that the גמרא Gemara
is plucking this as the criterion, you know, out of thin air,
and also assuming that there's no middle ground. Why can't it assume
that there's a type of a plaster that can count to be
משלים Mashlim but still doesn't count as water for a רביעית? Revi'it
Like why the גמרא Gemara just takes this for obvious that this
is the definition and either you're all on you know, if you're
on the good side then everything is good, if you're on the
bad side everything is bad, is a little strange. But anyway, let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
אלא לימותי יבחושים אדומים, Ela limutei yavshushim adumim, to exclude like little
red bugs like water bugs, you know, they believe that they were
created in the water or you know but they you know it's
they believed in spontaneous generation, but whatever, they live in the water,
these tiny little red dot water bugs. Okay and that's the type
of thing that because it comes from the water it counts as
enough as a water to get you to the ארבעים סאה, Arba'im
Seah, but you can't actually but it's only a minority of the
ארבעים סאה Arba'im Seah and you can't actually be טובל Tovel in
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אפילו בהנהו נמי, Afilu
beinhu nami, one minute, but if that's what you're talking about then
that should count totally like water and you could even be טובל
Tovel directly in it. Okay.
דהתניא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כל שתחילת ברייתו מן המים מטבילין
בו. De-ha tanya Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kol she-techilas briaso min
hamayim matbilin bo. If something was originally created in the water, again
it sounds like they believe in a type of spontaneous generation, okay
we can sort of say it was created it was born in
the water, not created from the water, but anyway it's treated as
water and you could actually be טובל Tovel in it. It's not
just משלים Mashlim and if you could be טובל Tovel in it
presumably you could use it also for you know for the רביעית
Revi'it of washing your hands. ואמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי מטבילין בעינו
של דג. Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi matbilin be-eino shel dag. If
you had a big fish eye, you know, and you liquefied it,
you know, you could be טובל Tovel in it. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara is basically still not finding anything in this
middle category. It assumes that this pourable plaster is
משלים Mashlim for everything and even for the רביעית Revi'it or it's
not משלים Mashlim thick enough that it doesn't count for anything. And
as far as these water bugs, it assumes that that's not even
משלים, Mashlim, that really counts as water. So where is this middle
case?
So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, so said רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, לימותי נתן סאה ונטל סאה. Limutei nasan sa'ah venatal sa'ah. We're
talking about the case where something doesn't just get you to the
ארבעים סאה, Arba'im Seah, it's not strong enough to get you by
itself to the ארבעים סאה, Arba'im Seah, but it will be משלים
Mashlim in the sense of if you have a מקוה Mikvah that's
ארבעים סאה Arba'im Seah and you put let's say one סאה Seah
of this in, so and the classic example of this, this is
another משנה Mishnah in מקואות, Mikvaos, is is like fruit juice, like
apple juice or orange juice. Okay, so that's obviously it's a liquid,
but it's it would not get you because it's not water, it
wouldn't get you thirty nine plus one unit of orange juice would
not get you to your ארבעים סאה. Arba'im Seah. But if you
have a ארבעים סאה Arba'im Seah מקוה Mikvah and you have one
unit of orange juice that falls in, and then you take out
one unit of water, even though the orange juice it's still now
thirty nine, one unit of orange juice, you know, you took out
the other unit from a different part of the מקוה Mikvah or
something like that, or maybe it has a tiny bit of the
orange juice in it, but most of the orange juice is still
there, nevertheless the מקוה Mikvah is כשר. Kosher Since it fell into
a כשר Kosher מקוה Mikvah and most of it... and the מקווה
Mikvah כשר Kosher. מקווה Mikvah was made up of water, this becomes,
this transforms into being considered water itself. So, okay, and then you
can even take out a unit of water and still be okay.
So, let's take a look. דתנן, Detnan, מקווה שיש בו מ"ם סאה
מכוונות, Mikvah sheyesh bo mem se'ah mechuvvanot, a מקווה Mikvah that had
exactly 40
סאה. Se'ah. נתן סאה ונטל סאה, Natan se'ah venatal se'ah, if you
put in a unit of this fruit juice, of orange juice, and
then you took out a unit from the מקווה, Mikvah, הרי זה
כשר, Harei zeh kasher, then the מקווה Mikvah is
כשר. Kosher. ואמר רב יהודה בר שילא אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן עד רובו. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda bar Shila amar Rav Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan ad rubo. You can keep on doing this again and
again and again until you now have 19 units of orange juice.
So you put in one unit of orange juice, you take out
a unit of water, another unit of orange juice, take out another
unit of water. Each unit that's going in, right, maybe you could
even put in 19 units at once and then take out 19
units. But as long as at the end in terms of the
actual content of the מקווה, Mikvah, what it physically consists of, we
know that it's a majority water, okay, then that's okay. Since as
the orange juice was going in, the מקווה Mikvah was already כשר.
Kosher, So orange juice is not enough to make a מקווה Mikvah
כשר, Kosher, it's not enough considered a type of a water to
make it כשר, Kosher. but it becomes part of the מקווה Mikvah
and as long as it only remains a minority as, you know,
even though you're putting in a unit and taking out a unit,
the מקווה Mikvah is כשר. Kosher So that's a type of a
משלים. Mashlim. A משלים Mashlim when you start with a כשר Kosher
מקווה. Mikvah. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is the משלים
Mashlim that works to make it a כשר Kosher מקווה Mikvah like
this plaster,
okay, the גמרא Gemara says if that makes it a כשר Kosher
מקווה Mikvah and it's enough like water that it makes it a
כשר Kosher מקווה, Mikvah, it should work even for a רביעית. Revi'it.
Okay, which again is funny because the הלכה Halacha is in the
משניות Mishnayot in מקוואות Mikvaot that this plaster gets you to the
40 but you still can't be טובל Tovel in it. But the
גמרא Gemara. assumes nope, if it gets you to the 40, then
it's totally enough like water, you know, that you can use it
also for the רביעית. Revi'it So we're talking about something like fruit
juices which don't get you to the 40, so they're not really
like water but they can become בטל Battel to the מקווה Mikvah
and that won't work when you're dealing with such a small שיעור
Shiur as a רביעית. Revi'it There you need that it all be
just pure water. Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes with it.
Okay, אמר רב פפא אם קדח בו רביעית מטבילין בו מחטין וצינוריות
הואיל ומכשירי דמקווה אתיא. Amar Rav Pappa im kodach bo revi'it matbilin
bo machten vetzinoryot hoilei me'achsherei de'mikvah atya. And here's that word קודח
again, which explains how תוספות read that earlier גמרא. Gemara, If you
carve out in your מקווה Mikvah a tiny little crevice, okay, so
in the wall of your מקווה Mikvah you carve out a little
crevice and water goes in and enough water, a רביעית of water
goes in, a רביעית is what you use for like a קידוש
cup, it's like three and a half ounces. So the הלכה Halacha
is that for טבילת כלים, Tvilat kelim, not for using a מקווה
Mikvah for a human being but for a
כלי, originally the הלכה Halacha is that you can use even a
מקווה Mikvah that just contains a רביעית of water. Okay, in the
end we say like they were מבטל Mevatel that, they don't let
us, you know, חז"ל Chazal said you're not allowed to do that,
but at least that's the original הלכה. Halacha.
But not if the whole מקווה Mikvah just contains a רביעית. Only
if that רביעית came from a כשר Kosher מקווה. Mikvah. So that's
very much like, you know, using the water in the כלי שרת
to wash the כהן's kohen? hands when it came from a basin
that had the right amount. So here's the same thing. It came
from a מקווה, Mikvah, it was a little thing on the side
of the מקווה, Mikvah, okay, so it came from the מקווה Mikvah
originally and it's somewhat still like connected, maybe not the waters aren't
touching, but you know, it's right there in the side of the
מקווה. Mikvah. So because it came from the water of a כשר
מקווה, Mikvah, you can use it for טבילה Tvila still, at least
טבילה Tvila for little, you know, needles and like רש"י sort of
says like, you know, like things that are used for spinning gold
or other types of forks and needles that can fit in that
little amount of water. So let's read that again. אמר רב פפא
אם קדח בו רביעית, Amar Rav Pappa im kodach bo revi'it, if
you, you know, carved out a little hole in the wall of
a מקווה Mikvah and there's now a רביעית of water in that
hole, מטבילין בו מחטין וצינוריות, Matbilin bo machten vetzinoryot, you can use
it for, you know, for being טובל Tovel like needles and other
like sort of like forks and other small little objects, הואיל ומכשירי
דמקווה אתיא, Hoilei me'achsherei de'mikvah atya, since it's coming from 40 סאה.
Se'ah.
All right. אמר רבי ירמיה אמר ריש לקיש מי מקווה כשרים למי
כיור. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya amar Reish Lakish mei mikvah ksheirim le'mei kiyor.
The waters you use for a מקווה Mikvah you can use for
the כיור. kiyor Because here's the question: where did the כיור, kiyor
the basin, get its water from? You know, it said that they
would lower it down into this well so it would not become
פסול בלינה. Pasul belina. But that, you know,
was that also the source of the water? Was it מים חיים?
Mayim chayim? Was it
a well? Water actually coming from underground or was it a cistern?
Can you use water that is rainwater for the מי כיור? mei
kiyor? Does the מי כיור mei kiyor only have to be water
that is what's called living water, water that comes from underground or
from a river or from an ocean? So what's the story?
So he says you can use yes, anything you could use for
a מקווה mikvah you could use for the כיור. kiyor למימרא דלא
מים חיים נינהו. l'maimra d'lo mayim chayim ninhu.
So it's saying that you don't need to have like living waters.
התניא דמתניתא ברייתא במים, atanya d'matnita braisa b'mayim, you know that it
says by the מקווה, mikvah, it says excuse me, by the, excuse
me, no this is about washing the parts of the animal after
it was שחט. shechted. והקרב והכרעים ירחץ במים. v'hakerev v'hakra'ayim yirchatz b'mayim.
Okay, so
that you wash them with water. And the ברייתא braisa teaches במים
ולא ביין, b'mayim v'lo b'yayin,
but you can't use wine to wash it. במים ולא במזג, b'mayim
v'lo b'mazag, you can't even use a mixture of wine and water.
במים לרבות שאר מים. b'mayim l'rabot shear mayim.
Okay, but says במים, b'mayim, I'm not exactly understanding, maybe the extra
ב bet or something, but other types of water also work. Okay,
what does other types of water mean? וקל וחומר למי כיור. v'kal
v'chomer l'mei kiyor. So and it's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer to
the waters of the כיור. kiyor Now, other waters רשי says means,
means like rainwater, okay? So it doesn't and certainly when it comes
to the כיור. kiyor Now, so what does that and those those
words mean? You can use to wash the limbs of the animal
rainwater, and certainly the כיור. kiyor So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
קל וחומר למי כיור? mai kal v'chomer l'mei kiyor? What does that
phrase mean? לאו דמים חיים נינהו? lav d'mayim chayim ninhu? It must
be assuming that the water of a כיור kiyor. is מים חיים,
mayim chayim, is
from an underground source or from a river or something of that
nature. And it's saying you can even use rainwater to wash the
limbs of an animal and certainly the type of water that you
use for a כיור, kiyor certainly מים חיים mayim chayim you can
use to wash the limbs of an animal. And that would clearly
imply that the or state that the waters of a כיור kiyor.
are מים חיים. mayim chayim. So isn't that what the ברייתא braisa
implies?
So
no, no, it says דקדיש, d'kadish, וקדישים, v'kadishim, so
no, it doesn't mean that. It means you can certainly use not
the water that you would use for the כיור, kiyor that's not
what it means. It means you can use use water from the
כיור kior, that was sanctified by the כיור. So if you can
use normal water, rainwater, whatever to wash the limbs, you can certainly
use כיור water. Why is כיור water a חידוש? So first the
גמרא, Gemara I mean not a חידוש, why is it obvious that
that's good? So the first reason the גמרא Gemara said was because
it was מים חיים. mayim chayim. But then it says no, maybe
you don't need מים חיים. mayim chayim. Okay, so now the reason
it's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer and it's obvious that the כיור
water is good is because it was sanctified, so certainly sanctified water
you should be able to use. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, וקדישים מעליותא היא? v'kadishim alyusa hi? Is sanctified water a plus
here, a benefit when it comes to washing the legs of the
animals that it would be a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? והתניא רבי
ישמעאל מים שאין בהם שם לוואי. vehatanya Rabbi Yishmael mayim she'ein bahem
shem l'vay. But what we taught in the ברייתא braisa that רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says when it says that you have to wash
the limbs of the animal with water, it means water that does
not have a modifying name. Okay, so if you call it something
like spring water or כיור waters or holy waters, then you can't
use it. It has to be just water. יצאו מי כיור שיש
להם שם לוואי, yatzu mei kiyor sheyesh lahem shem l'vay, so you
can't use the water of a כיור because they have a modifying
name. So presumably the modifying name is the מי כיור mei kiyor
or holy water. So the גמרא Gemara says if what so so
how do you how do you balance these? On the one hand
it says not מי כיור mei kiyor and the other ברייתא braisa
says you can use מי כיור mei kiyor to wash the limbs.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying well no, what that means is
you can't actually use the מי כיור mei kiyor because that has
a modifying name, okay, but you can use the waters that you
would use for the מי כיור. mei kiyor. מים חיים mayim chayim
is what you could use to wash the limbs. It's even a
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. So now we're back to saying that it
sounds like you use מים חיים mayim chayim for the basin because
the ברייתא braisa made it a קל וחומר kal v'chomer for washing
the limbs.
It's funny that it doesn't assume that מים חיים mayim chayim has
a שם לוואי. shem l'vay. All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says אלא לאו דראויים למי כיור. ela lav d'reuyan l'mei kiyor. So
therefore we can't actually use the waters of the כיור because that
would have a modifying name. So it must mean waters that in
theory could be used for the כיור. אלמא מים חיים נינהו. alma
mayim chayim ninhu.
So you see that clearly what this ברייתא braisa means is you
can use rainwater for washing the limbs and קל וחומר kal v'chomer
spring water and מים חיים, mayim chayim, קל וחומר kal v'chomer you
could use the water for a כיור that would be used for
a כיור. So you see that the כיור would only use מים
חיים. mayim chayim. That's what the גמרא Gemara is says it suggest
you know this is reading this ברייתא. braisa. So it actually concedes
the point. תנאי היא. tanai hi. Fine.
That's what that ברייתא braita assumes, but it's a debate of תנאים.
tannaim. דאמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan, מי כיור, mei kiyor, רבי
ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer, מי מים הן, mei mayim hein, וחכמים
אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, שאר מימות הן, she'ar meimot hein, that is according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that it
has to be from a wellspring, but according to the חכמים chachamim
you can use any water. And to the degree that there's פסק
psak here, that's how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק. paskens. Okay, so what
we have seen is that the כיור,
you know, has to contain the water for four כהנים, it can
be any water, it doesn't have to be מים חיים, mayim chayim,
and a whole interesting question about, like, you know, putting in orange
juice and taking it out and being משלים mashlim a שיעור shiur
etc. Okay, let's now move on to the next part. ערל. arel.
So now that we had a whole lovely long discussion around the
idea that, you know, about the כהנים, you know, that they had
to be wearing all of their בגדים, bgadim, it led us to
a discussion of בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, then they had to have
their hands washed and their feet, and if not then the עבודה
avoda is, the קרבן korban is, you
know, is פסול pasul
based on the word like חלל, chalal, it's desecrated. Okay, and now,
so that led us to a whole long discussion about the washing
of the hands and the basin, and now we're moving on to
the next one, ערל, arel, an uncircumcised person. Now, who is this
uncircumcised כהן? kohen רש"י says it's somebody from a family of hemophiliacs,
it's not something that's actively rejecting, you know, the מצוה mitzvah of
ברית מילה, bris milah, that person would be like a מומר, mumar,
a, you know, a מין, min, and we'll see that that's somebody
who rejects תורה מצוות Torah mitzvos, is also excluded from serving in
the בית המקדש, no surprise there. So it's somebody because of a
medical reason. תוספות says it would even include somebody who doesn't want
to get a ברית מילה bris milah because of fear, you know,
of the pain of it. Of course, why he didn't get it
as an infant, I don't know, but anyway, but as long as
it's not a principled rejection, that's who we're talking about. Okay, מנלן,
menalan, how do you know that an uncircumcised כהן kohen, cannot serve?
And that if he serves that the, you know, עבודה avoda is
מחולל, mechulal, and the קרבן korban is פסול? pasul? אמר רב חסדא,
amar Rav Chisda, דבר זה מתורת משה רבינו לא למדנו. davar zeh
miTorat Moshe Rabbeinu lo lamadnu. You didn't get it from משה'ס Moshe's
תורה. Torah מדברי יחזקאל בן בוזי למדנו, midivrei Yechezkel ben Buzi lamadnu,
we got it from יחזקאל, Yechezkel, which is sort of shocking because
you're not supposed to get anything that's not originally from the תורה.
Torah. So we'll see what the גמרא Gemara has to say about
that. כל בן נכר ערל לב וערל בשר לא יבוא אל מקדשי.
kol ben neichar arel lev v'arel basar lo yavo el mikdashi. Any
foreigner who is of uncircumcised heart or uncircumcised flesh cannot come to
My sanctuary. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומנלן דמחלי עבודה, umenalan demachli
avoda, fine, that says it's prohibited, but bracketing now that this is
all coming from יחזקאל, Yechezkel, where do you see that it, you
know, that it desecrates, that it makes the עבודה avoda invalid? דכתיב,
dechtiv, בהביאכם בני נכר ערלי לב וערלי בשר להיות במקדשי לחלל את
ביתי, behavi'achem benei neichar arelei lev v'arelei basar lihyot bemikdashi l'chalel et
beiti, when they brought those foreigners of uncircumcised heart and of uncircumcised
flesh to be in My sanctuary to desecrate. So once you have
the word לחלל, l'chalel, it means the עבודה avoda is מחולל. mechulal.
Okay, so that's the פסוקים. psukim. So
now we have to figure out how we, what's this בן נכר,
ben neichar, ערל לב, arel lev, and still also, you know, ערל
בשר arel basar is pretty clear, and then we have to figure
out how you can get it from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, rabbis taught. בן
נכר, ben neichar, יכול בן נכר ממש, yachol ben neichar mamash, maybe
it really means a, you know, a non-Jew. Of course, that'd be
crazy, a non-Jew can't be a כהן, what's the הוה אמינא? hava
amina? תלמוד לומר ערל לב. talmud lomar arel lev. No, no, no,
the next phrase ערל לב arel lev is explaining what a בן
נכר ben neichar is, somebody who has made himself foreign because he
has rejected תורה Torah. and מצוות. mitzvos That's how we're going to
read it. So uncircumcised heart, he has alienated himself, right, from from
from the world of from God. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר בן
נכר? im kein mah talmud lomar ben neichar? So why do you
have to say בן נכר? ben neichar? שנתנכרו מעשיו לאביו שבשמים. shenitnachru
ma'asav l'aviv shebashamayim.
So it doesn't really explain why you needed to say both, but
like it explains what the words בן נכר ben neichar mean. Okay,
that they have alienated themselves from God. רש"י says if you look
at רש"י, שנתנכרו מעשיו, shenitnachru ma'asav, second line from the top, okay,
נחשבים לנכרים למקום, nechshavim l'nochrim l'makom,
maybe to tell us that they are considered as if they are
non-Jews. That gets to the whole question, you know, מחלל שבת, mechalel
Shabbat, you know, רמב"ם Rambam has a phrase that he uses a
lot, it's like a non-Jew, doesn't mean it's fully halachically, but it's
a very harsh way of conceptualizing and of excluding, this concept that
it is seen as if you're completely outside the fold. So that's
ערל לב. arel lev. Okay, ואין לי אלא ערל לב, v'ein li
ela arel lev, so that's somebody who rejects, but ערל בשר מנין,
arel basar minayin, how about somebody who just doesn't have a ברית
מילה? bris milah? תלמוד לומר וערל בשר, talmud lomar v'arel basar, that's
the next words. וצריכי, v'tzrichi, and you need to say both. דאי
כתב רחמנא ערל בשר משום דמאיס, de'ei katav Rachmana arel basar mishum
de'ma'is, if the תורה Torah just excluded somebody who was uncircumcised, that's
because it's, like, repugnant, meaning the guy didn't do anything wrong, especially
רש"י'ס Rashi's from a family of hemophiliacs, but you know, the תורה
Torah is concerned when it comes to the כהנים, it's a בית
המקדש. aesthetics matter and nobody is looking there but God is looking,
and the same way there are מומין mumin that are invalid even
if they're
not visible to people, this is just considered somebody that is it's
not appropriate. It's disgusting from an aesthetics sort of type of perspective.
אבל ערל לב דלא מאיס aval arel lev d'lo ma'is but somebody
that's like an אפיקורס apikorus or rejecting תורה מצוות, Torah mitzvos,
there's nothing at the aesthetic level that is repulsive. Okay, so אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe that person would not be excluded, it would
not certainly be מחלל עבודה. mechalel avodah. ואי אשמעינן ve'i ashmi'inan ערל
לב arel lev משום דאין לבו לשמים. mishum d'ein libo lishmayim. Now
if it just said the person who rejected תורה Torah מצוות, mitzvos.
okay, they're not part of the community and they're not doing it
לשם שמים leshem shamayim the עבודה. avodah. אבל ערל בשר דלבו לשמים
aval arel basar d'libo lishmayim אימא לא, eima lo, but somebody who
just doesn't have a ברית מילה bris milah who's doing the עבודה
לשם שמים, avodah leshem shamayim, his essence is somebody לשם שמים, leshem
shamayim, maybe that would not be a problem. צריכי, tzrichi, it needs
to tell both. Now the גמרא Gemara here, so that's how you
learn it out based on יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Now the גמרא Gemara here
doesn't say what about the fact that it's not from תורת משה,
Toras Moshe, it does say it's not תורת משה, Toras Moshe, it
doesn't say how to solve the problem, but the גמרא actually earlier
said that and it basically said we have to assume that this
was a מסורה masorah and we always knew it was sort of
like a תורה שבעל פה Torah she'be'al peh and in the end
יחזקאל Yechezkel said it out loud. Okay, but it is pretty shocking
when the גמרא is prepared to do that, something that really straight
out say we're not even going to try to find a basis
for it in the תורה Torah itself. Okay, we'll end here now
we'll pick up tomorrow with the category of טמא. tamei.